<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cryptomator Blog</title><description>Recent Blog Posts on cryptomator.org</description><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/tags/vault-format/</link><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><image><url>https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/logo.png</url><title>Cryptomator Blog</title><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/tags/vault-format/</link></image><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 07:14:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><generator>Hugo</generator><item><title>BitLocker, the FBI, and the Illusion of Control</title><description>&lt;p>When it recently became known that &lt;strong>Microsoft had helped the FBI decrypt BitLocker-encrypted data carriers&lt;/strong>, there was widespread outrage. People were quick to talk about “backdoors,” broken encryption, and how BitLocker was clearly unreliable. But as is so often the case, the real problem lies less in the technology itself than in &lt;strong>who has control over the encryption key&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This case is a good opportunity to take a closer look: What really happened? Why was access possible? And what does this say about &lt;strong>our understanding of encryption and cloud services&lt;/strong>?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/microsoft-bitlocker.png" alt="BitLocker, the FBI, and the Illusion of Control" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="what-happened">What Happened?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The case that came to light involved a &lt;strong>criminal investigation&lt;/strong> in which the FBI seized several laptops. These devices were encrypted with &lt;strong>BitLocker&lt;/strong>, the &lt;strong>hard disk encryption feature integrated into Windows&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The FBI was still able to decrypt the data &lt;strong>because Microsoft was able to provide the corresponding recovery keys&lt;/strong>. These keys were &lt;strong>stored in the Microsoft account of the person&lt;/strong> concerned. Microsoft was legally obliged to disclose this information by court order.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is important to clarify one thing: &lt;strong>Microsoft did not “crack” BitLocker&lt;/strong>. There was no security breach, no secret master key, and no technical backdoor into the encryption itself. &lt;strong>Microsoft was able to help because they had the keys.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="bitlocker-is-securebut-not-automatically-private">Bitlocker Is Secure—But Not Automatically Private&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>BitLocker is technically considered a &lt;strong>robust encryption solution&lt;/strong>. The data on a device cannot be read without the appropriate key. The problem does not arise with encryption, but with &lt;strong>key management&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By default, &lt;strong>Windows offers to save the BitLocker recovery key in your Microsoft account&lt;/strong>. This is convenient because if you forget your password or change your hardware, you can simply retrieve the key online.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, &lt;strong>this convenience has a consequence&lt;/strong>: if Microsoft holds the key, Microsoft also has the ability to pass it on—for example, to law enforcement agencies with the appropriate warrant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Encryption therefore only fully protects data from third parties if the key remains exclusively under the control of the user.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-real-misunderstanding-encryption--key-control">The Real Misunderstanding: Encryption ≠ Key Control&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Many users equate encryption with complete control. In practice, however, this is often not the case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A rough distinction can be made between:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Client-side encryption with external key management&lt;/strong>. This means that the provider has access to the key.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Zero-knowledge encryption&lt;/strong>. Here, the provider has no technical access to the key.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>BitLocker with a cloud-backed recovery key clearly falls into the first category. The &lt;strong>data is encrypted, but not exclusively for the owner.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The Microsoft case therefore does not demonstrate a failure of BitLocker&lt;/strong>, but rather a &lt;strong>structural problem with modern cloud ecosystems&lt;/strong>. Convenience features often undermine data sovereignty without anyone noticing.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-many-are-surprised">Why Many Are Surprised&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The strong reaction to this case shows one thing above all else: &lt;strong>many people do not know where their encryption keys are stored.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cloud backups, automatic synchronization, and preset security options are standard today. They lower the barrier to entry, increase user-friendliness, and quietly shift responsibility from the user to the provider.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This leads to a misleading assumption:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“My data is encrypted, so no one can access it.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Technically correct would be:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“My data is encrypted, but someone else has the spare key.”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="access-by-authorities-is-not-a-special-case">Access by Authorities Is Not a Special Case&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another important point: &lt;strong>Access by authorities is not an unusual scenario.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If providers have access to keys or unencrypted data, they are &lt;strong>legally obliged&lt;/strong> in many countries to hand them over if ordered to do so. &lt;strong>This applies not only to Microsoft, but also to other major cloud providers.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The crucial question is therefore not:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Do I trust Microsoft?”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>But rather:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>“Do I want to give a provider the technical ability to decrypt my data?”&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="what-users-can-learn-from-this">What Users Can Learn From This&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The case offers a valuable lesson&lt;/strong> – regardless of the specific product:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Encryption is only as strong as key management&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cloud backups of keys always mean a loss of control&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Security is not a default setting, but a conscious decision&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you want maximum privacy, you also have to take responsibility for keys&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>This does not mean that cloud services are fundamentally insecure&lt;/strong>. But it does mean that you should understand which security model you are using and what compromises it entails.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-cryptomator-helps-in-such-cases-zero-knowledge-instead-of-key-storage">How Cryptomator Helps in Such Cases: Zero Knowledge Instead of Key Storage&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is precisely where solutions such as &lt;strong>Cryptomator and Cryptomator Hub&lt;/strong> come in. Unlike many integrated encryption functions, Cryptomator consistently follows a &lt;strong>zero-knowledge principle&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This means that &lt;strong>data is encrypted locally on the device&lt;/strong> before it can even be uploaded to the cloud. The key difference lies in key management. &lt;strong>Cryptomator does not store passwords, recovery keys, or master keys.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Neither cloud providers nor Cryptomator itself have technical access to the encrypted content or the keys required to decrypt it. Even if a cloud service—such as Microsoft OneDrive, Google Drive, or Dropbox—were required to disclose data, &lt;strong>it would only contain unreadable, encrypted files&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>difference is particularly clear&lt;/strong> in the context of the BitLocker case:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>With BitLocker and a cloud-backed recovery key, the provider can issue the key&lt;/li>
&lt;li>With Cryptomator, this key only exists with the user themselves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Access by third parties is technically impossible, not just organizationally&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This &lt;strong>deliberately shifts responsibility back to the users&lt;/strong>. It requires a little &lt;strong>more personal responsibility&lt;/strong>—for example, when it comes to handling passwords securely—but in return &lt;strong>offers a significantly higher degree of control and privacy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This model is particularly important for sensitive data of any kind. You can&amp;rsquo;t pass on something you don&amp;rsquo;t own yourself.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion-encryption-is-not-a-feature-but-a-responsibility">Conclusion: Encryption Is Not a Feature, but a Responsibility&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The BitLocker-FBI case &lt;strong>does not reveal a secret backdoor or a breach of modern cryptography&lt;/strong>. It reveals something much more fundamental: how easily we trade control for convenience – often without even realizing it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>True data sovereignty does not come from encryption alone, but from exclusive control over the keys. Anyone who relinquishes this control should at least be aware of what that means.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Or to put it another way: &lt;strong>Do you know who has your encryption key?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2026/02/15/bitlocker-fbi-and-the-illusion-of-control/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2026/02/15/bitlocker-fbi-and-the-illusion-of-control/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>microsoft</category><category>bitlocker</category></item><item><title>Digital Independence Day: Why Digital Independence Is Important</title><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Every first Sunday of the month&lt;/strong> this year, people around the world take a moment to reflect on their digital habits. The occasion is &lt;strong>Digital Independence Day&lt;/strong> — a day of action for digital self-determination, privacy, and independence from tech monopolies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But what does &lt;strong>digital independence&lt;/strong> actually mean? And more importantly: How can you take your first steps without completely changing your digital everyday life or investing a lot of time and energy?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/digital-independence-day-2026.png" alt="Digital Independence Day 2026" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-digital-independence-day">What Is Digital Independence Day?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Digital Independence Day is an initiative that encourages people to &lt;strong>reduce their dependence on large, centralized tech platforms&lt;/strong> — especially those whose business models are based on data collection, lock-in effects, and a lack of transparency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead of calling for radical change, the movement deliberately focuses on &lt;strong>small, practical steps&lt;/strong> that are accessible to everyone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the &lt;strong>official &lt;a href="https://di.day/">Digital Independence Day&lt;/a> website&lt;/strong>, you’ll find ideas, tools, and easy guides to help you get started right away — from communication and social media to cloud storage and online services.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At its core, Digital Independence Day stands for:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>less dependence&lt;/strong> on tech monopolies&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>more control&lt;/strong> over your own data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>conscious use&lt;/strong> of privacy-friendly alternatives&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="why-digital-independence-matters">Why Digital Independence Matters&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Today, much of our digital lives takes place on just a few platforms. They store our documents, organize our communication, and influence which information we see.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This &lt;strong>concentration of power&lt;/strong> has consequences:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>loss of data sovereignty&lt;/li>
&lt;li>opaque data usage and profiling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>limited freedom of choice&lt;/li>
&lt;li>political and economic dependencies&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Digital independence &lt;strong>does not mean rejecting technology&lt;/strong>. It means &lt;strong>regaining agency&lt;/strong> and using tools that respect users, promote openness, and enable real control over data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="digital-independence-doesnt-have-to-be-complicated">Digital Independence Doesn’t Have to Be Complicated&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There is a common assumption that digital independence requires technical expertise or hours of research. In reality, many impactful steps can be taken &lt;strong>in just a few minutes&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are a few examples inspired by Digital Independence Day:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>1. Try decentralized social networks&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Instead of relying on a centralized platform like Facebook or X, you can try decentralized networks such as &lt;strong>Mastodon&lt;/strong>. Mastodon works similarly to traditional social networks, but it is not controlled by a single company. You can choose a provider, switch if needed, and still stay connected to the entire network.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The official &lt;a href="https://di.day/category/rezepte/">Digital Independence Day&lt;/a> website offers easy starting points and explanations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>2. Be more conscious about cloud storage&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cloud services are convenient, but they often mean that &lt;strong>unencrypted data is stored with third-party providers&lt;/strong>. A simple first step toward digital independence is &lt;strong>client-side encryption&lt;/strong>: your files are encrypted before they leave your device. This is exactly where &lt;strong>Cryptomator&lt;/strong> comes in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With Cryptomator, you can continue using your existing cloud provider &lt;strong>while staying in control of your data&lt;/strong>. The provider stores only encrypted files — the keys remain with you. No provider switch. No complicated setup. But significantly more control.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>3. Replace one tool at a time&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You don’t have to change everything at once. Instead, start by &lt;strong>focusing on one area&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>messaging&lt;/li>
&lt;li>cloud storage&lt;/li>
&lt;li>social media&lt;/li>
&lt;li>password management&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Replace just one tool with a more &lt;strong>privacy-friendly alternative&lt;/strong>. That alone is already a meaningful step. &lt;strong>Digital independence is a process&lt;/strong> — not a to-do list. That’s why Digital Independence Day focuses on small actions that anyone can easily take in everyday life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-we-support-digital-independence-day">Why We Support Digital Independence Day&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At Cryptomator, we believe that &lt;strong>privacy and control should not be a luxury&lt;/strong>. They should be the standard and accessible to everyone. Digital Independence Day aligns perfectly with this belief. It empowers people to make informed decisions without pressure and without fear-mongering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That’s why we support the initiative and invite our community to take part — not just for one day, but continuously.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="digital-independence-day-special--february-edition">Digital Independence Day Special — February Edition&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To support your first (or next) step toward digital independence, we’re continuing our campaign: On the &lt;strong>first Sunday of February&lt;/strong>, we’re giving away &lt;strong>100 Cryptomator voucher codes — for free&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The codes will be shared on our social media channels and are available on a &lt;strong>first come, first served&lt;/strong> basis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our goal: to lower the barrier to entry and make digital self-determination accessible to as many people as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="your-next-step">Your Next Step&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Digital independence doesn’t require perfection. It starts with awareness and grows with every conscious decision. If you’re looking for inspiration, practical guides, and simple alternatives: &lt;strong>Visit the &lt;a href="https://di.day/">official Digital Independence Day website&lt;/a>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And if you want to take control of your cloud data today: &lt;strong>Encrypt your files with Cryptomator before they go to the cloud.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2026/02/01/digital-independence-day-2026/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2026/02/01/digital-independence-day-2026/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>did</category></item><item><title>Winter Is Coming: 50% off Cryptomator</title><description>&lt;p>Winter is Coming — and this time it brings not only cold, but also data security at half the price! From December 1 to 31, 2025, our Winter Sale is live, giving you &lt;strong>50% off*&lt;/strong> Cryptomator.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That means: only &lt;strong>€9.99 instead of €19.99&lt;/strong> — and as a &lt;strong>one-time purchase&lt;/strong>, not a subscription, with no monthly fees.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cryptomator.org/for-teams/">&lt;strong>Cryptomator Hub&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> is also available at a &lt;strong>50% discount&lt;/strong> for the first year! Contact us for more detailed terms and conditions or take a look at our &lt;a href="https://cryptomator.org/de/pricing/#for-teams">&lt;strong>price list&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/pricing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/winter-2025-sale.png" alt="Cryptomator Winter Sale 50% Off" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="pay-once-stay-protected-forever">Pay Once, Stay Protected Forever&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At Cryptomator, we strongly believe that privacy &lt;strong>shouldn’t require a subscription&lt;/strong>.&lt;br>
While many apps rely on monthly or yearly fees, Cryptomator stays true to its &lt;strong>one-time purchase&lt;/strong> model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once purchased, you can use Cryptomator indefinitely — &lt;strong>with no recurring costs or hidden charges&lt;/strong>. Your data stays protected, free from subscription traps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="price-change-coming-in-2026">Price Change Coming in 2026&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Starting &lt;strong>January 1, 2026&lt;/strong>, the price of Cryptomator will increase to &lt;strong>€29.99&lt;/strong>.&lt;br>
This ensures long-term investment in &lt;strong>security standards, performance, and new features&lt;/strong> that will continue to protect you reliably in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So if you&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about getting Cryptomator, &lt;strong>now is the perfect time&lt;/strong>. Secure not only the 50% discount but also the &lt;strong>old price&lt;/strong> before winter ends.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="get-protected-before-the-year-ends">Get Protected Before the Year Ends&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>“Winter is Coming”&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> — but your data can be prepared. Use December to secure your digital information and benefit from our biggest discount of the year.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After December 31, the Winter Sale ends — and the price goes up. &lt;strong>Buy now and stay protected for good.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/12/01/winter-sale/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/12/01/winter-sale/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>sale</category></item><item><title>Confidentiality Is a Must: Why Works Councils Need Encryption</title><description>&lt;p>Works councils play a central role in companies when it comes to &lt;strong>protecting the interests of employees&lt;/strong>. In doing so, they process &lt;strong>particularly sensitive data&lt;/strong> on a daily basis: personal complaints, election results, meeting minutes, or confidential agreements with trade unions. All of this information is not only subject to a &lt;strong>moral obligation of confidentiality&lt;/strong>—it also falls under the strict requirements of the &lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/compliance/gdpr/">&lt;strong>GDPR&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But how can a works council fulfill this responsibility in the digital age, when documents are often stored, shared, and edited collaboratively in the cloud? The answer lies in a combination of &lt;strong>technical security, organizational processes&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>the right tools&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/encryption-for-works-councils.png" alt="Why Works Councils Need Encryption More Than Ever" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="sensitive-data-requires-special-protective-measures">Sensitive Data Requires Special Protective Measures&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Personnel data, sick notes, conflict discussions, internal processes—&lt;strong>works councils have deep insights into the innermost workings of the company&lt;/strong>. This information concerns not only labor law disputes or restructuring, but also very personal situations in the lives of employees.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The GDPR requires such personal data to be protected with appropriate technical and organizational measures. This explicitly includes &lt;strong>encryption&lt;/strong>. This measure is not an optional extra, but a &lt;strong>central component of works council work&lt;/strong> that complies with data protection regulations.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-encryption-is-not-always-the-same">Why Encryption Is Not Always the Same&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Many companies today already rely on &lt;strong>cloud-based systems such as Microsoft 365 or Google Workspace&lt;/strong>. These solutions advertise built-in security and encryption. However, what many people don&amp;rsquo;t know is that this often involves &lt;strong>server-side encryption&lt;/strong>, which means that although the data is encrypted, the provider or administrator has the keys. Anyone who has access to the system can also access the data. This applies in particular to internal company administrators or external service providers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is not sufficient for particularly sensitive information, such as that processed by works councils. &lt;strong>End-to-end encryption&lt;/strong> is required here: only authorized persons can access the content – even cloud providers or central IT departments have no access. The key to access remains exclusively with the works council.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="digital-sovereignty-with-cryptomator-hub">Digital Sovereignty With Cryptomator Hub&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/for-teams/">&lt;strong>Cryptomator Hub&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> provides works councils with a tool that meets precisely these requirements. The solution enables the creation of encrypted data rooms (known as vaults) that can be used on any common cloud platform – while &lt;strong>remaining entirely under the control of the council&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Vaults can be structured according to topics, roles, or working groups&lt;/strong> – for example, for minutes, election documents, complaints, or legal advice. &lt;strong>Access rights can be assigned granularly&lt;/strong> via a clear interface. For example, only the election committee is authorized to access election documents, while other members have access to general meeting minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another advantage: the &lt;strong>Web of Trust&lt;/strong> principle allows the committee to integrate new devices and members on a trust basis – &lt;strong>without any central IT management or external administration&lt;/strong>. This is how digital self-administration becomes a reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="integration-without-it-dependency">Integration Without IT Dependency&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;strong>common obstacle&lt;/strong> for works councils is their &lt;strong>dependence on their employer&amp;rsquo;s IT infrastructure&lt;/strong>. What if the company itself provides the cloud platform? Or what if the works council does not operate its own technical infrastructure?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cryptomator Hub works independently of the underlying cloud&lt;/strong>. This means that even if the company provides Dropbox, OneDrive, or Nextcloud, the works council can securely encrypt its content without the employer having access. &lt;strong>Control over the key and access structure remains exclusively with the committee&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It can also be used on &lt;strong>private devices&lt;/strong>, which is an important factor for smaller works councils or committees without their own office infrastructure.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Confidentiality is not a nice-to-have, but a legal obligation and a responsibility that must be upheld. Works councils facing digital transformation &lt;strong>should view the protection of sensitive data as a key requirement&lt;/strong>—not only to comply with legal requirements, but also to maintain the trust of the workforce.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With end-to-end encryption and independent tools such as Cryptomator Hub, works councils can fulfill this obligation &lt;strong>securely, easily, and independently&lt;/strong>. And in doing so, they can send an important message: for digital maturity, for data protection, and for modern co-determination on an equal footing.&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/24/encryption-for-works-councils/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/24/encryption-for-works-councils/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>hub</category></item><item><title>Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0 is here!</title><description>&lt;p>We are pleased to announce the &lt;strong>official release of Cryptomator Desktop version 1.18.0&lt;/strong>. Following the &lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/09/26/desktop-beta-1.18.0/">beta phase&lt;/a>, this version brings the full package of improvements, new features, and stability enhancements—now available for all supported platforms.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/desktop-1.18.0.png" alt="Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="new-features-whats-new-in-1180">New Features: What’s New in 1.18.0?&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="restoring-the-vault-configuration-file">Restoring the Vault Configuration File&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>recovery key&lt;/strong> has been part of Cryptomator for some time, but with version 1.18.0, it is now significantly more powerful: You can now &lt;strong>completely restore lost or damaged master key files and vault configuration files&lt;/strong> using your existing recovery key.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Whether accidentally deleted, overwritten due to a backup problem, or damaged by a memory error, the vault can now be &lt;strong>reliably reconstructed&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This makes the recovery key a real emergency tool that secures access to the vault in case of an emergency and prevents complete data loss.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/recover-vault-config.png" srcset="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/recover-vault-config.png 1x, https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/recover-vault-config@2x.png 2x" alt="Restoring the vault configuration file" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="new-signature-certificates-for-windows">New Signature Certificates for Windows&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The Windows installer and all binary files are &lt;strong>signed with a new certificate&lt;/strong>. The old certificate is no longer valid, and the new certificate ensures smooth installation on modern Windows systems without disruptive warning dialogs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="remembering-the-last-vault-location">Remembering the Last Vault Location&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When creating a new vault, Cryptomator now automatically suggests the &lt;strong>last location used&lt;/strong>. Users who create multiple vaults in similar folder structures benefit from a &lt;strong>significantly faster setup process&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="bug-fixes--platform-improvements">Bug Fixes &amp;amp; Platform Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="macos-26-correct-display-of-the-app-icon--and-no-squircle-jail-for-cryptomator">macOS 26: Correct Display of the App Icon – And No &amp;ldquo;Squircle Jail&amp;rdquo; for Cryptomator&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>On macOS 26 (codename &amp;ldquo;Tahoe&amp;rdquo;), the &lt;strong>Cryptomator icon&lt;/strong> was put inside a generic grey squircle, which didn&amp;rsquo;t look right. This issue has been fixed in version 1.18.0, so the icon now appears as it should.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With Tahoe, Apple now enforces squircle-shaped icons for all macOS apps—similar to the strict guidelines that have always applied to iOS. Previously, macOS apps could escape the squircle more freely, and many apps used this playfully as part of their visual identity. But now, app icons must conform to the squircle shape. We&amp;rsquo;re joining the &lt;strong>squircle resistance&lt;/strong> alongside other app developers who are keeping their distinctive icon designs instead of conforming to this new guideline.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/squircle-jail-resistance.png" srcset="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/squircle-jail-resistance.png 1x, https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/squircle-jail-resistance@2x.png 2x" alt="macOS 26: Correct Display of the App Icon – And No 'Squircle Jail' for Cryptomator" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="macfuse-detection-on-macos-26">macFUSE Detection on macOS 26&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Some users experienced problems integrating vaults because macFUSE was not always recognized on macOS 26. This bug has now been fixed, so vaults can be opened reliably again.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="windows-control-over-log-file-sizes">Windows: Control Over Log File Sizes&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In rare cases, log files on Windows could grow enormously and cause system problems. The size limit of the log files has been corrected so that Cryptomator runs reliably and conserves resources in the background again.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="linuxkde-cleaning-up-quickaccess-entries">Linux/KDE: Cleaning Up QuickAccess Entries&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Under KDE, the Dolphin file manager created a new QuickAccess entry every time a vault was unlocked—even if one already existed, for example after the app was unexpectedly closed. This behavior has now been corrected. Existing entries are reused, and unnecessary duplications are a thing of the past.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-changes--technical-updates">Further Changes &amp;amp; Technical Updates&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Update of the UI framework to JavaFX 25&lt;/strong>: improved performance, modern graphics display, and long-term compatibility.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>New “Share” entry in the context menu&lt;/strong> that explains how to share vaults.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Various &lt;strong>security and library updates&lt;/strong> (including nimbus-jose-jwt, logback, commons-lang3, dagger) to keep the software up to date and secure.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="why-this-update-is-important">Why This Update Is Important&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Version 1.18.0 makes Cryptomator Desktop &lt;strong>more robust, user-friendly, and better prepared for future operating system versions&lt;/strong>. The new recovery feature protects in critical scenarios (e.g., damaged configuration files), while UI and system improvements make everyday use of Cryptomator smoother.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-you-can-do-now">What You Can Do Now&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Install Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0 for your operating system.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you have been using the &lt;strong>beta version&lt;/strong>, please be sure to update to the final release!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For businesses and security-conscious users, it&amp;rsquo;s worth taking a look at the &lt;strong>new Windows certificate&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And remember: &lt;strong>keep your vault recovery key safe&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="closing-remarks">Closing Remarks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Thank you&lt;/strong> to everyone in the community who tested the beta. Your &lt;strong>feedback&lt;/strong> directly contributed to making 1.18.0 a strong, stable release. With this update, Cryptomator Desktop is more reliable than ever!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thank you for using Cryptomator—and thank you for securely encrypting your data.&lt;br>
We look forward to your feedback on the new release!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your Cryptomator Team&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/19/desktop-1.18.0/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/19/desktop-1.18.0/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>desktop</category></item><item><title>Two Years of Cryptomator Hub – Team Encryption Reimagined</title><description>&lt;p>On &lt;strong>November 2, 2023&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Cryptomator Hub 1.0&lt;/strong> was released—our solution for secure, encrypted collaboration in the cloud. &lt;strong>Two years&lt;/strong> later, Cryptomator Hub has become a central tool for companies, universities, and NGOs that want to protect their sensitive data while working efficiently as a team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On this anniversary, we look back on two exciting years full of further developments, beta features, new areas of application—and what&amp;rsquo;s yet to come.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/hub-anniversary-2025.png" alt="Two Years of Cryptomator Hub – Team Encryption Reimagined" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-cryptomator-hub">What is Cryptomator Hub?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Cryptomator Hub is the &lt;strong>central platform for managing and sharing encrypted vaults&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the classic Cryptomator app allows individuals to protect their cloud files, the Hub extends this principle to teams and organizations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cryptomator Hub offers a web-based dashboard that administrators and team members can use to &lt;strong>manage users, assign roles, and control access rights&lt;/strong>—all fully encrypted and GDPR-compliant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cryptomator Hub thus bridges the gap between strong &lt;strong>end-to-end encryption&lt;/strong> and user-friendly teamwork.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="features-that-make-the-difference">Features That Make the Difference&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Centralized Management of Users and Permissions&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a small team or a large organization, administrators can always keep track of who has access to which vaults. Role-based permissions make management easy and transparent.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Web of Trust&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
This security model enables secure key exchange between team members via digital trust relationships. No unencrypted data exchange and no complicated key files, as trust is mapped technically.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Create Vault Role&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Teams can independently create new vaults without administrators having to accompany each step. This keeps collaboration flexible while maintaining a high level of security.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Self-Hosting &amp;amp; Data Protection by Design&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Data protection is not an add-on, but a core principle: Cryptomator Hub can be operated locally (on-prem) or in private cloud environments. This gives companies and institutions complete control over their infrastructure and data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Integration with Popular Cloud Services&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Whether OneDrive, Google Drive, Dropbox, or Nextcloud, Cryptomator Hub integrates seamlessly into existing work environments and protects data regardless of the provider.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="typical-areas-of-application">Typical Areas of Application&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="companies-and-public-authorities">Companies and Public Authorities&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Companies use Cryptomator Hub to implement zero-trust security strategies. &lt;strong>Industries with high compliance requirements&lt;/strong>—such as healthcare, public administration, and legal services—benefit particularly from GDPR-compliant cloud encryption.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Companies such as &lt;a href="">Walbusch GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG&lt;/a> are already successfully using Cryptomator Hub and can report consistently positive results:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>With Cryptomator Hub, we can securely manage sensitive company data while making it easy for our employees to use.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Andreas Cofalla, Application Manager IT, Walbusch GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG&lt;/em>&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="universities-and-research-institutions">Universities and Research Institutions&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Research teams secure their project data with Hub without sacrificing cloud collaboration. &lt;strong>Sensitive research data&lt;/strong> remains protected while collaboration across departments or countries continues to function.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ngos-and-nonprofits">NGOs and Nonprofits&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For organizations operating globally, Cryptomator Hub offers a secure way to share &lt;strong>confidential documents&lt;/strong>—from grant proposals to personnel data—even with limited IT resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="it-teams-and-data-protection-officers">IT Teams and Data Protection Officers&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Hub simplifies audits, role management, and verification of data protection-compliant working practices—a clear advantage in internal and external security audits.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="two-years-of-further-development--and-looking-to-the-future">Two Years of Further Development – And Looking to the Future&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Since its launch in 2023, Cryptomator Hub has developed rapidly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/04/15/hub-1.4.0/">1.4.0 update&lt;/a> in April 2025 brought two decisive milestones with the &lt;strong>Web of Trust&lt;/strong> and the &lt;strong>Create Vault role&lt;/strong>. Furthermore, everything is focused on optimization, scaling, and future-proofing—especially with regard to the upcoming standards of &lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/07/24/post-quantum-roadmap/">post-quantum cryptography&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But we are not resting on our laurels. &lt;strong>Three new features&lt;/strong> are already in the pipeline to make Cryptomator Hub even more powerful and user-friendly.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="usergroup-management">User/Group Management&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>User and group management&lt;/strong> will become much more convenient in the future. With the new, &lt;strong>integrated user/group management&lt;/strong>, smaller companies and organizations can create and manage their team structures directly in the hub—intuitively, clearly, and without detours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the background, we continue to rely on &lt;strong>Keycloak&lt;/strong>—a proven, powerful solution for identity and access management.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/hub-anniversary-2025-user-management-preview.png" alt="Cryptomator Hub – User/Group Management Preview" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="emergency-access">Emergency Access&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In companies, it can always happen that employees leave and access to important data is lost as a result.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The upcoming &lt;strong>Emergency Access&lt;/strong> feature provides a remedy here: it allows you to &lt;strong>designate a specific group of authorized persons&lt;/strong> who can restore access to a vault, either collectively or partially, in an emergency.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Even in critical situations or in the event of personnel changes&lt;/strong>, the company remains capable of acting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/hub-anniversary-2025-emergency-access-preview.png" alt="Cryptomator Hub – Emergency Access Preview" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h3 id="files-in-use-in-the-desktop-app">Files in Use (in the Desktop App)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A frequently expressed wish of our Hub customers: &lt;strong>better support for collaborating on Office files.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While &lt;strong>LibreOffice&lt;/strong>, for example, already has a built-in locking system for open files, this has been missing in &lt;strong>Microsoft Office&lt;/strong> until now. That&amp;rsquo;s why we are currently developing our own &lt;strong>“locking system”&lt;/strong> in the &lt;strong>Cryptomator desktop app&lt;/strong> that recognizes when a file is already open and informs other users.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This makes collaborating on documents more conflict-free, transparent, and secure—another step toward smooth teamwork.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="two-years-of-trust-cooperation-and-security">Two Years of Trust, Cooperation, and Security&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In two years, Cryptomator Hub has evolved from an idea into a reliable platform for secure teamwork.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We would like to thank all users, administrators, and testers who have helped to further develop Cryptomator Hub with their feedback—and we look forward to the next chapter.&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/02/hub-anniversary/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/11/02/hub-anniversary/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>hub</category><category>anniversary</category></item><item><title>OneDrive Security Breach Shows: Why Zero-Knowledge Matters</title><description>&lt;p>In &lt;strong>May 2025&lt;/strong>, the &lt;strong>Oasis Security&lt;/strong> published an &lt;a href="https://www.oasis.security/blog/onedrive-file-picker-security-flaw-oasis-research">analysis&lt;/a> that caused a stir in the cloud world: &lt;strong>a vulnerability in OneDrive File Picker&lt;/strong> allowed third-party applications to access files for which they did not actually have access rights. &lt;strong>Millions of users&lt;/strong> were affected, both private individuals and companies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What exactly happened, why is this incident so explosive, and what can you learn from it to better protect your own data?&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/onedrive-security-breach.png" alt="OneDrive Security Breach Shows: Why Zero-Knowledge Matters" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="what-went-wrong-with-onedrive-file-picker">What Went Wrong With OneDrive File Picker?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>OneDrive File Picker is a popular interface that allows apps to access files from personal cloud storage. However, Oasis Security discovered that &lt;strong>certain configuration&lt;/strong> errors allowed applications to view and download files that they did not officially have access to – even sensitive content such as tax documents, project plans, or confidential meeting minutes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Worse still, the affected applications did not even need to use an exploit – all they had to do was use the File Picker correctly (or rather, incorrectly). &lt;strong>The problem was not a targeted hack, but a design flaw in the system.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-real-lesson-trust-is-not-a-security-concept">The Real Lesson: Trust Is Not a Security Concept&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Many users trust cloud providers such as Microsoft, Google, and Apple to keep their data secure. But this incident shows that even large platforms make mistakes—with far-reaching consequences.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>real problem&lt;/strong> runs deeper:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Access rights&lt;/strong> are managed in the backend, not by the user(s) themselves.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Files are often stored &lt;strong>unencrypted&lt;/strong> on servers—or only with a key that the provider itself controls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Security vulnerabilities in third-party apps or web interfaces&lt;/strong> can be exploited without those affected even noticing.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>In short&lt;/strong>: anyone who entrusts their data exclusively to the security promises of cloud providers is relinquishing control.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-solution-zero-knowledge-encryption-with-cryptomator">The Solution: Zero-Knowledge Encryption With Cryptomator&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Cryptomator takes a fundamentally different approach: &lt;strong>files are encrypted locally on your device before being uploaded to the cloud&lt;/strong>. This means your data remains protected even if the cloud provider is compromised—or, as in the case of OneDrive, simply makes a mistake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No one&lt;/strong> but you can read your files—not Microsoft, not Google, not us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Access rights&lt;/strong> are secondary, because without the key, all data remains unreadable.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Even &lt;strong>compromised&lt;/strong> APIs or third-party apps only see encrypted garbage data.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Cryptomator Hub&lt;/strong> offers the ideal extension for teams, organizations, and companies:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Centralized management of encrypted vaults&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
IT administrators can preconfigure vaults and share them with specific users—all with end-to-end encryption.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Role-based access control&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Thanks to the role-based system, you can specify exactly who is allowed to create, open, or manage vaults—without central key distribution.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Web of trust for secure collaboration&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Team members verify each other, creating a trustworthy environment—without the need for external certificate authorities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Seamless integration into existing cloud workflows&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Cryptomator Hub can be easily combined with existing cloud storage solutions such as OneDrive, Google Drive, or Dropbox.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Cryptomator Hub enables &lt;strong>highly secure and practical cloud usage within teams&lt;/strong> without the usual compromises in data protection and compliance. This is a future-proof solution, especially for organizations with increased requirements, such as &lt;strong>NGOs, research institutions, or companies in regulated industries&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-you-can-do-now">What You Can Do Now&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Whether you use OneDrive, Dropbox, or another cloud service, this incident shows that &lt;strong>no provider can offer 100% security&lt;/strong> on its own. However, you can drastically reduce your risks by taking a few simple steps:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Use &lt;strong>client-side encryption&lt;/strong> with tools such as Cryptomator.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not store particularly sensitive documents unencrypted in the cloud.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Raise awareness among your team members&lt;/strong> or colleagues about cloud access rights.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check which third-party apps have access to your cloud.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion-safety-begins-with-control">Conclusion: Safety Begins With Control&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The OneDrive security breach is not an isolated incident—it is a symptom of a system that relies on trust rather than real control. But if you &lt;strong>encrypt your files before uploading them&lt;/strong>, you remain protected even in the event of serious security breaches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With Cryptomator, you retain full control over your data, your privacy, and your digital security.&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/10/17/onedrive-security-breach/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/10/17/onedrive-security-breach/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>onedrive</category></item><item><title>Back to School – Data Security for Universities</title><description>&lt;p>With the start of the new winter semester, lecture halls are filling up again—as are the &lt;strong>digital platforms of universities&lt;/strong>. Learning management systems, research platforms, cloud storage solutions, and digital administrative processes have long been part of everyday life at universities. But while digitalization opens up new opportunities, it also carries risks: &lt;strong>cyberattacks, data breaches, and inadequately protected cloud data&lt;/strong> jeopardize the integrity and confidentiality of highly sensitive information. In this article, we show why encryption is essential for universities – and how it helps make &lt;strong>research, teaching, and administration more secure&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/back-to-school.png" alt="Back to School – Data Security for Universities" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="why-universities-are-a-lucrative-target-for-cyberattacks">Why Universities Are a Lucrative Target for Cyberattacks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Universities and colleges process a wide range of sensitive data:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Personal data&lt;/strong> of students, researchers, and employees (e.g., student ID numbers, transcripts, health information).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Research data&lt;/strong>, often related to third-party funding or government-funded projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>International collaborations&lt;/strong>, which also require compliance with the regulations of other countries (e.g., FERPA, GDPR).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Login details and access keys&lt;/strong> for learning platforms, email services, and digital resources.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>More and more attacks are targeting universities, for example through ransomware, phishing, or cloud leaks. According to the &lt;a href="https://www.bsi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/EN/BSI/Publications/Securitysituation/IT-Security-Situation-in-Germany-2024.html">BSI Situation Report 2024&lt;/a>, educational institutions are among the critical areas with a sharply increased threat level. This makes it all the more important for universities to make their digital structures resilient and encrypted.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="encryption-the-universitys-digital-invisible-ink">Encryption: The University’s Digital Invisible Ink&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Data encryption protects information using mathematical methods—it can only be read with the right key. For universities, this means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Confidentiality of research results&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Particularly in the case of sensitive basic research or cooperation projects with companies, it is crucial that only authorized persons have access to files. End-to-end encryption protects this data even if a cloud provider is compromised.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data protection for students and teachers&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
The EU GDPR requires universities to comprehensively protect personal data. Encryption enables data processing that complies with data protection regulations—even when using the cloud, working from home, or using BYOD models.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Protection against ransomware and data loss&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Encrypted backups and protected storage systems can greatly limit the impact of ransomware attacks. Attackers have no access to unencrypted original data, and recovery can take place without payment.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="practical-application-where-encryption-makes-sense">Practical Application: Where Encryption Makes Sense&lt;/h2>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>&lt;strong>Field of application&lt;/strong>&lt;/th>
&lt;th>&lt;strong>Recommended solution&lt;/strong>&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Cloud storage (e.g., Nextcloud, OneDrive)&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Client-side encryption with tools such as Cryptomator&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Research data archiving&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Zero-knowledge cloud or encrypted vaults&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Administrative documents&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Password protection and structured access controls&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Mobile use &amp;amp; working from home&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Container-based encryption on mobile devices&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion-set-the-course-now-for-a-safe-semester">Conclusion: Set the Course Now for a Safe Semester&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The digitization of higher education is unstoppable—but it is not defenseless. Those who encrypt today will protect the autonomy of research and teaching tomorrow. Universities that rely on simple, secure, and privacy-compliant encryption solutions build trust among students, employees, and partner institutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now is the ideal time to evaluate existing systems, raise awareness, and integrate encryption solutions for the long term.&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/10/10/back-to-school/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/10/10/back-to-school/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>university</category></item><item><title>Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0 Beta – Try it now!</title><description>&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/desktop-1.18.0-beta.png" alt="Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0 Beta" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The next release of Cryptomator Desktop is right around the corner – and before we publish the final version, we&amp;rsquo;d like to invite you to test the beta of version 1.18.0. Along with useful new features and important bug fixes, this release also comes with a special call to our community.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="new-features--fixes">New Features &amp;amp; Fixes&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>With Cryptomator Desktop 1.18.0, we’re once again bringing improvements and bug fixes across all platforms:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="new-feature">New Feature&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Remember Last Vault Location&lt;br>
When creating a new vault, Cryptomator will now automatically suggest the last chosen storage location. This makes setup more convenient, especially if you manage multiple vaults in similar folder structures.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="fixes">Fixes&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Linux/KDE: QuickAccess Entries&lt;br>
On KDE, each unlock process created a new QuickAccess entry in the Dolphin file manager, even if one already existed (e.g., after an unexpected app crash). This is now fixed – existing entries are reused, and no manual cleanup is needed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Prevention of Huge Log Files&lt;br>
On Windows, log files could in rare cases grow extremely large, causing system issues. The existing size limit of log files was bypassed in those cases. This has been fixed, so the app can safely run in the background without issues.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>macOS: Stability When Saving Vault Passwords&lt;br>
Some users experienced app crashes when trying to save a vault password. This bug has now been fixed, so password saving on macOS works reliably.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>macOS: macFUSE Detection on macOS 26&lt;br>
In the upcoming macOS version 26, macFUSE was sometimes not detected, leading to problems when mounting vaults. This issue is fixed to ensure Cryptomator works smoothly on the latest macOS releases.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="text-center">
&lt;a href="https://github.com/cryptomator/cryptomator/releases/tag/1.18.0-beta1/">&lt;i class="fa-solid fa-download">&lt;/i> Download the Beta 1.18.0 here&lt;/a>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="we-need-your-support">We Need Your Support!&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In addition to these updates, there’s something special this time:&lt;br>
Our Windows installer is now signed with a new certificate. Since this certificate is not yet widely recognized in Microsoft’s trust network, Windows may display a security prompt when installing the beta version.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The more people install the beta, the faster the certificate will gain trust – and the security dialog will disappear. Don’t worry: the installer is still safe and signed by us. Windows just needs to “learn” that the new certificate is trustworthy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="final-words">Final Words&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>With version 1.18.0, we’re making Cryptomator more convenient, stable, and future-proof. The beta is an important step – not only to test the new features and fixes, but also to establish our new certificate in the Windows ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We’re grateful for every bit of support from the community:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Install the beta and try out the updates.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Share your feedback if you notice anything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Help us make the final release as stable and user-friendly as possible.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Your feedback makes Cryptomator stronger – and ensures we can all keep our data securely encrypted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thank you for your support – we can’t wait for the final release of 1.18.0! 🎉&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/09/26/desktop-beta-1.18.0/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/09/26/desktop-beta-1.18.0/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>desktop</category><category>beta</category></item><item><title>Cryptomator Autumn Sale: Protect Your Data – and Your Wallet!</title><description>&lt;figure class="text-center">
&lt;a href="https://staging.cryptomator.org/pricing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
&lt;img class="inline-block rounded-sm" src="https://staging.cryptomator.org/img/blog/autumn-2025-sale.png" alt="25% Off Cryptomator" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>When the days get shorter and the leaves fall, it&amp;rsquo;s time to refresh not only your wardrobe but also your digital security. Our fall offer helps you keep your data well protected throughout the darker months of the year.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From &lt;strong>September 22&lt;/strong> to &lt;strong>30&lt;/strong>, the &lt;strong>Cryptomator Autumn Sale&lt;/strong> is live – and that means:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>25 % off&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://cryptomator.org">Cryptomator&lt;/a>&lt;br>
With Cryptomator, you can encrypt your files locally before they go to the cloud—no complicated configuration or additional accounts required.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>25 % off&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://cryptomator.org/hub">Cryptomator Hub&lt;/a> for the first year&lt;br>
Cryptomator Hub enables centralized management, user roles, and audit logs—perfect for NGOs, educational institutions, and companies that take data protection seriously.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Whether you&amp;rsquo;re looking to encrypt your &lt;strong>personal cloud&lt;/strong> or secure &lt;strong>sensitive data in your organization&lt;/strong> – now is the perfect time to get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>📦 The discount applies to &lt;strong>all editions&lt;/strong> – including &lt;strong>team and business solutions&lt;/strong>.&lt;br>
📅 Act fast! The offer is only available for a &lt;strong>limited time&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Get the deal now!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Stay safe. Stay encrypted.&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Your Cryptomator Team&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/09/22/autumn-sale/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://staging.cryptomator.org/blog/2025/09/22/autumn-sale/</guid><category>cryptomator</category><category>sale</category></item></channel></rss>